A Guide to the Secretary of Technology, 1998-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Secretary of Technology, 1998-2002
Library of Virginia
38993, 39659
8.70 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Unknown, transferred 10 January 2002 (accession 38993). Unknown, transferred 4 June 2002 (accession 39659).
Biographical/Historical Information
In February 1997, the House of Delegates passed a resolution requestion "the Governor appoint a Technology and Science Advisor within his Cabinet to advise him with regard to technological and scientific issues in Virginia and assist him and executive branch agencies with the potential reorganization or restructuring of Virginia state government in response thereto." James S. Gilmore III, a Republican candidate for Governor, proposed in an April 23, 1997 speech the creation of a Cabinet-level post for an information technology officer. After his election as Governor in November 1997, Gilmore kept his campaign promise. On May 21, 1998, Gilmore issued Executive Order Number Nine, creating the Office of the Secretary of Technology. The new Secretary's responsibilities included the "coordinated planning and effective development of information technology resources" in Virginia. Gilmore appointed Donald W. Upson, a vice president of Litton/PRC Inc., an information technology company, and former senior Republican committee staff member in Washington, as the first Secretary of Technology. The Secretary of Technology possessed Cabinet-level status but was not officially made a permanent member of the Governor's cabinet until 1999.
The Secretary of Technology is appointed by the governor and subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Information Technology, Department of Technology Planning, Center for Innovative Technology, and the Virginia Information Providers Network Authority. Governor Mark R. Warner retained Donald W. Upson, the first Secretary of Technology, in an interim capacity through February 2002. George C. Newstrom, Governor Warner's selection for Secretary of Technology, began work in March 2002. Newstrom previously worked with EDS, a global technology services company.
Scope and Content Information
The records of the Secretary of Technology consist of constituent correspondence to the Governor referred to the secretary for response, appointment calendars, and correspondence and subject files. Constituent correspondence are arranged by tracking numbers assigned by the Governor's office and date received. Subjects included are general technology issues, Internet pornography, Internet regulations, Internet tax and electronic commerce, SPAM and telecommuting.
Donal W. Upson, Secretary of Technology, wrote responses to most of these letters and electronic messages. The bulk of this collection consists of the Secretary's appointment calendars from June 1998 to January 2002. These records document the various events the secretary was invited to and attended. Included are correspondence, faxes, and e-mail messages to Fionna Matheson, the secretary's scheduler, coordinating the secretary's schedule and travel. Event information is also included. Additional correspondence are arranged by subject. Notable topics include the Center for Innovative Technology, Governor's Commission on Information Technology, Council on Information Management, Century Date Change Initiative (Y2K), Department of Information Technology, Department of Technology Planning, and various public relations, activities, and visits by the secretary.
Contents List
- Constituent Correspondence-1998-2000
  - Correspondence Numbers 31503-49386 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers 49463-51245 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers 51459-62580 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers 62608-64062 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers 64429-69461 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Numbers 69730-74899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Numbers 74973-78920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence Numbers 78996-81790 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Numbers 81937-86207 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Numbers 86212-92663 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Numbers 92345-95009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Numbers 95127-96912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence Numbers 97060-98508 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence Numbers 98625-100745 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence Numbers 100753-103444 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Numbers 103460-107266 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Numbers 108021-110486 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence Numbers 110775-2011280 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2009130-2008723 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Constituent Correspondence-2000-2001
  - Correspondence Numbers 2004643-2009769 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2010353-2019979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2026629-2029832 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2030803-2039406 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2040464-2045160 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Constituent Correspondence-2001
  - Correspondence Numbers 2050551-2059626 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2060148-2069865 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2070107-2081843 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers 2082053-2085197 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Appointments Calendar
  - June 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - July 1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - July 1998-Cox Fibernet Visit, 21 July 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - August 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - September 1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - October 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - November 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - December 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - January 1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - February 1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - March 1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - April 1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - May 1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - June 1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - July 1-19, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - July 20-31, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - [August 1999- See Box 9, Accession 39659]
  - September 1-20, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - September 21-30, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - October 1-12, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - October 13-21, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - October 22-31, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Appointments Calendar
  - November 1-14, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - November 15-30, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - December 1-12, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - December 13-31, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - January 1-18, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - January 19-31, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - February 1-11, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - February 12-29, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - March 1-16, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - March 17-31, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - April 1-12, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - April 13-24, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - April 25-30, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - May 1-8, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - May 9-16, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - May 17-22, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - May 23-31, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - June 1-6, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - June 7-18, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - June 19-30, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Appointments Calendar
  - July 1-11, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - July 12-16, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - July 17-20, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - July 21-29, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - July 30-31, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - August 1-14, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - August 15-23, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - August 24-31, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - September 1-12, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - September 13-18, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - September 19-20, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - September 21-26, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - September 27-30, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - October 1-6, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - October 7-11, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - October 12-15, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - October 16-22, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - October 23-25, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - October 26-31, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Appointment Calendars
  - November 1-9, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - November 10-15, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - November 16-21, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - November 22-30, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - December 1-10, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - December 11-15, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - December 16-31, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - January 1-12, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - January 13-20, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - January 21-31, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - February 1-6, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - February 7-20, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - February 21-28, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - March 1-4, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - March 5-13, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - March 14-19, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - March 20-29, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - March 27-31, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Appointments Calendar
  - April 1-5, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - April 6-21, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - April 22-25, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - April 26-30, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - May 1-9, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - May 10-15, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - May 16-22, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - May 23-31, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - June 1-10, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - June 11-22, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - June 23-30, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - July 1-14, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - July 15-23, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - July 24-31, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - August 1-11, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - August 12-20, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - August 21-31, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Appointments Calendar (1999, 2001-2003) [Accession 39659]
  - August 1-12, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - August 13-31, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - September 1-11, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - September 12-17, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - September 18-30, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - October 1-11, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - October 12-18, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - October 19-23, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - October 24-31, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - November 1-12, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - November 13-15, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - November 16-30, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - December 1-10, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - December 11-17, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - December 18-31, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - January 1-19, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - January 20-29, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - January 30-31, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Appointment Calendar (accession 38993)
  - Calendar 1998 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Calendar 1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Calendar 2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Calendar 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Center for Innovative Technology (CIT)
  - Recommendations (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Commission on Information Technology FIles
  - Establishment (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1st Meeting, December 1-2, 1998, College of William and Mary (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 2nd Meeting, May 12, 1999, Abingdon, Virginia (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 2nd Meeting, May 12, 1999, Abingdon, Virginia-Reports (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 3rd Meeting, September 1, 1999, George Mason University (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Regional Meetings, October 1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - 4th Meeting, December 9, 1999, Old Dominion University-Press Kit (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - 4th Meeting, December 9, 1999, Old Dominion University-Norfolk Information (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - 4th Meeting, December 9, 1999, Old Dominion University-Invitations (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - 4th Meeting, December 9, 1999, Old Dominion University-Presentations (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Reports (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Wrap-Up Meetings, August 31, 2000, Richmond, Virginia (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Correspondence-State Agencies
  - Council on Information Management (CIM) (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Century Date Change Initiative (CDCI) (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Department of Information Technology (DIT) (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Department of Technology Planning (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Correspondence-Secretary of Technology, Chronological
  - 1998 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - 1999 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - 2000 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - 2001 (Box 10, Folder 25)
- Decision Briefs
  - 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 26)
- Electronic Mail, Official Records
  - 2000 (contains one record referring to a DSS Executive Summary) (Box 10, Folder 27)
- Projects and Studies-Department of Technology Planning
  - 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 28)
- Projects and Studies-Department of Information Technology
  - 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Waivers (Box 10, Folder 30)
- Projects and Studies-eGovernment Implementation Office
  - 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 31)
- Public Relations, Activities and Visits
  - 2001 Global Internet Summit, George Mason University, March 5-9, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - 2000 Global Internet Summit, George Mason University, March 12-14, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Technology Outreach, First Symposium, VCU, November 9, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Technology Outreach, Second Symposiu, Alexandria, January 11, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Technology Outreach, Third Symposium, Newport News, February 15, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Technology Outreach, Fourth Symposium, Abingdon, April 26, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Virginia Link (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - "First" NASA Project (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - .com Summit (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Internet2- Virginia Tech Event, June 1, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Commerce Committee Testimony, June 9, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Advisory Commission on E-Commerce Meeting, June 21-22, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Small Business Innovative Research Conference, September 22-23, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - COVITS Symposium, September 29-30, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - February 9, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 46)
- Trip Planning Records
  - Hong Kong (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - World Congress (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - London (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - CEBIT/Colorado/Seattle (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - International Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Governor's Trade Mission, April-May 2001 (Box 10, Folder 53)